Guide to the Gilmore D. Clarke papers, 1927-1982
Clarke, Gilmore D.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gilmore D. Clarke papers, 1927-1982, 1937-1974 (bulk)
15-1-808
Gilmore D., Clarke 1892-
4 cubic ft.
Photographs, correspondence, clippings
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists primarily of correspondence documenting Clarke's unsuccessful campaign to prevent the demolition of Cornell University's Boardman Hall and its replacement by Olin Library. Also included are addresses, published Christmas sonnets by Clarke, 1968-1980, 1982, clippings, articles, letters to the editor (Ithaca Journal and the New York Times), photographs, campus maps, and photocopies of letters, including two from Harry S. Truman concerning Clarke's opinion on remodelling part of the White House (1947). Represented in the collection are Bernhard Louis Clynes, John Lyon Collyer, George Bain Cummings, Edmund Ezra Day, Arthur Hobson Dean, C.W. DeKiewiet, Douglass Boardman Lee, Thomas W. Mackesey, Deane W. Malott, Floyd Roy Newman, Jerome O'Connor, Nathaniel Alexander Owings, Gustav Jaeger Requardt, and Allen Hosie Treman.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Landscape architect, civil engineer, professor of city and regional planning.
Gilmore D. Clarke graduated from Cornell University in 1913, and joined the faculty there in 1935. He was a partner in the New York firm of Clarke and Rapuano, Inc., chairman of the National Commission of Fine Arts from 1937-1950, the head of a White House remodelling project, a member of the board of design of the 1939 World's Fair, and an architectural consultant on the United Nations headquarters and other projects in New York and Washington.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists primarily of correspondence documenting Clarke's unsuccessful campaign to prevent the demolition of Cornell University's Boardman Hall and its replacement by Olin Library. Also included are addresses, published Christmas sonnets by Clarke, 1968-1980, 1982, clippings, articles, letters to the editor (Ithaca Journal and the New York Times), photographs, campus maps, and photocopies of letters, including two from Harry S. Truman concerning Clarke's opinion on remodelling part of the White House (1947). Represented in the collection are Bernhard Louis Clynes, John Lyon Collyer, George Bain Cummings, Edmund Ezra Day, Arthur Hobson Dean, C.W. DeKiewiet, Douglass Boardman Lee, Thomas W. Mackesey, Deane W. Malott, Floyd Roy Newman, Jerome O'Connor, Nathaniel Alexander Owings, Gustav Jaeger Requardt, and Allen Hosie Treman.
Approximately 150 mounted gelatin silver print photographs of projects Clarke designed as landscape architect for the New York City Park Commission, ca. 1930- 1937. Approximately 400 photographs of projects Clarke designed as landscape architect for the Westchester County (N.Y.) Parks Commission, especially the Bronx River Parkway, ca. 1925-ca. 1937, including one photograph of Franklin Delano Roosevelt, ca. 1925.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Clarke, Gilmore D., 1892-; Clynes, Bernhard Louis.; Collyer, John Lyon, b. 1893.; Cummings, George Bain, b. 1890.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; De Kiewiet, C. W.(Cornelius William), 1902-; Dean, Arthur H.; Lee, Douglass B.; Mackesey, Thomas W.(Thomas William), 1908-1976.; Malott, Deane W.(Deane Waldo), 1898-; Newman, Floyd R.(Floyd Roy), 1890-1990.; O'Connor, E. Jerome, 1891-1977.; Owings, Nathaniel Alexander, 1903-; Requardt, Gustav J. (Gustav Jaeger).; Treman, Allan H., 1899-1975.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Cornell University--Buildings.; Cornell University--Planning.; Cornell University.Libraries.; White House (Washington, D.C.)
Subjects:
Campus planning.; Christmas--Poetry.; Express highways--New York (State)--Westchester County.; Historic buildings--Conservation and restoration.; Landscape architecture--New York (N.Y.); Landscape architecture--New York (State)--Westchester County.; Landscape architecture--United States--Designs and plans.; Parks--New York (State)--Westchester County.; College teachers.; Planners.; Urban parks.; Zoos.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collection:Clarke and Rapuano records, #3047.
Related collection:Cornell University Architectural Advisory Council records, #43-3-496.
CONTAINER LIST
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1930-1937, undated; Includes images of Bronx Parkway Extension, Bronx River Parkway, Saw Mill River Parkway, Hutchinson River Parkway, and Glen Island Park (Box 1)
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1936-1939, undated; Includes images of Astoria Pool, Bryant Park, Washington Square Park, Columbus Park, Ten Eyck Houses, Battery Park, Barrett Park Zoo, 1936 World's Fair, Tri-Borough Bridge, Roosevelt Avenue Bridge, Battery Bridge (proposed design), Thomas Jefferson Swiming Pool, and Pelham Bay Park Golf House (Box 2)
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1936, undated; Includes images of Astoria Pool, Prospect Park Zoo, Chrystie-Forsyth Playground, Bryant Park, Claremont Park, Flushing Meadow Park, Fort Tryon Park, Madison Square Park (proposed design), Thomas F. Smith Park, Washington Square Park, Zach's Bay, Jones Beach, Thomas Jefferson Swimming Pool, Central Park Zoo, Chisholm Park, City Hall Park (proposed design), Bushwick Park, and Carl Shurz Park (Box 3)
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1929-1933, undated; Includes images of Glen Island Park, V. Everett Macy Park, Palmer-Central Avenue Bridge, Tibbetts Brook Park, Hutchinson River Parkway, Cross County Parkway, New York Eastern State Parkway, and New State Parkway (Box 4)
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1930-1937, undated; Includes images of Cross County Parkway, Bronx River Parkway Extension, Bronx River Parkway, Hutchinson River Parkway, Ten Eyck Houses, Grand Central Parkway, Henry Hudson Parkway, Saw Mill River Parkway, and Tibbetts Brook Park (Box 5)
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1927-1937, undated; Includes images of Saw Mill River Parkway, Rye Beach, New York Eastern State Parkway, Bronx River Parkway, and Bronx River Parkway Extension (Box 6)
- Mounted photographs of various locations in New York, 1930-1937, undated; Includes images of Hutchinson River Parkway, Glen Island Park, Poundridge Reservation, Sprain Brook Parkway, Saw Mill River Parkway, Bronx River Parkway Extension, Grand Central Parkway, and Rye Beach (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1937-1951 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Correspondence and news clipping, 1953-February 1957 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and news clippings, March 1957 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and news clippings, April 1957 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, May-September 1957 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Correspondence and news clippings, January-February 1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Correspondence and news clipping, March-April 1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Correspondence and news clippings, May-December 1958 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Correspondence and news clippings, January 1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Correspondence and news clippings, February-March 1959 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, news clippings, and sonnets, April 1959-1963 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Addresses and invitation, 1950-1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Sonnets, 1970-1982 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Photographs of structures or drawings, most unidentified, made for the Westchester County Park Commission, Undated (Box 9)
- Photographs of structures or drawings, most unidentified, made for the Westchester County Park Commission, Undated; Also includes an image of Franklin Delano Roosevelt giving a speech, possibly taken at the dedication of the Bronx River Parkway on November 5, 1925 at Valhalla, New York in Westchester County (Box 10)
- 11 matted and inscribed photographs of bridges designed for the Westchester County Park System, Undated (Folder 1-2)